Rowley, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1664-1941.
Congregational Library Archives
Rowley, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1664-1941.
RG4836
Congregational Library Archives
0.67 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes, 7 reels)
The First Church of Rowley, Mass. was founded in 1639 by Rev. Ezekiel Rogers and his followers, who had departed their Anglican church in Rowley, Yorkshire, UK in protest over lax Sabbath laws. Rev. Rogers was a notable Puritan whose conservative zeal influenced the governance of the Massachusetts Bay Colony. The church continues to serve the community today as a member of the United Church of Christ. This collection contains the earliest church, parish, and financial records beginning in 1664, and microfilmed versions of the records also include more recent administrative records.
First Church (Rowley, Mass.)
Phillips, Samuel, 1725-1796
Jewett, Jedidiah, 1705-1774
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were permanently loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church, Rowley (UCC) in August 2011. There is no accession number for this collection.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Custodial History
The earliest volume of church records, 1664-1784 (also known as the "Phillips Diary") was assumed lost by the church during the later 20th century, but was recovered in 2007 from a deposit box in the Rowley branch of the First National Bank of Ipswich. The volume was extensively conserved by the Northeast Document Conservation Center in 2010 and microfilmed shortly afterwards.
Microfilm records, 1664-1784 were created in 2010 from the physical volume of church records 1664-1748 (also known as the "Phillips Diary"). The microfilm was imaged and produced by the Northeast Document Conservation Center.
Microfilm records, 1664-1941 were copied in 2007 from the original negatives loaned by the church, which have no known provenance.
Microfilm records, 1730-1835 were imaged and produced in 2008 by the Northeast Document Conservation Center.
Historical Note
The original founders of the church and town of Rowley, Mass. came from the town of the same name in the East Riding of Yorkshire, UK. Rev. Ezekiel Rogers, the leader of the settlers, was the assistant pastor at St. Peter's Church of England in Rowley, and a staunch supporter of puritanical observance of the Sabbath. He found himself at odds with the Anglican authorities, who issued a decree allowing the playing of sports on Sundays. He and at least 21 families separated themselves in protest and left for the New World on the ship John, settling in the area in 1638. The land for the settlement was purchased for 800 pounds from Newbury and Ipswich, and the town was officially incorporated on September 4, 1639. The settlers brought with them a high level of expertise in the manufacture of cotton, hemp and flax cloth, and constructed the first fulling mill in America.
The first meeting house was erected at the intersection of Central Street (then Holmes Street) and Wethersfield Street, and dedicated on December 3, 1639. This building was used for Sunday services and Lecture Days (midweek services) in addition to secular town business.
Rev. Rogers became a persuasive leader in the development of the puritanical government of the Court of Massachusetts Bay Colony. He was one of four ministers from Essex County chosen to rule on questions of church and colonial law, and the first recorded preacher at a council of Congregational Churches in New England. Less puritanical members were offended by his religious zeal; among his strong beliefs was that private members should not make speeches in church assemblies.
Rev. Rogers was married three times; his first two wives, Joan Hartopp and Joan Nelson, both died in childbirth along with the child. He married the widow Mary Barker in July of 1651. On the night of the marriage, Rev. Roger's home, furnishings, library, and church records were destroyed by a fire, popularly believed to be arson by a woman whom Rev. Rogers had refused to marry. Shortly after the fire he fell from his horse and broke his right arm, which became permanently useless. He died in 1660 and was buried in the Rowley Cemetery.
The Rev. Samuel Phillips (Harvard College, 1650) was settled in June, 1651, as a teacher on a salary varying from £50 to £90 per annum. When Rev. Rogers's health began to seriously decline, Mr. Phillips largely took over the ministry despite his lay status, and the town selectmen ordered that £5 should be paid to him for this service. This led to a protracted 18-year dispute with Rev. Rogers's widow, who claimed that the funds had been appropriated illegally. The case was decided in her favor by the Ipswich court, but was later overruled by the Massachusetts General Court in 1679.
In 1665, Samuel Shepard (Harvard College, 1658) was ordained pastor of the church, Mr. Phillips still acting as teacher. After Rev. Shepard's death in 1668, Mr. Phillips was finally ordained as pastor and continued in the role until his death in 1696.
In 1695 the town voted to build a new meeting house, and construction was completed in May of 1697. All notified persons were required to assist with the construction or be fined three shillings per day. This second building measured 50x40 feet and included a gallery and glass windows transferred from the previous meeting house. It also featured benches which were partitioned into men and women's seating areas.
Construction began on a third meeting house in 1747, which measured 60x42 feet with a steeple on the north side and porch on the south. The interior featured a large pulpit and sounding board and a broad aisle with galleries to the front and sides. In August of 1777 the meeting house was damaged by a lightning strike. Repairs were withheld until 1781, after the end of the Revolutionary War, using funds acquired from the auctioning off of space for additional pews.
In 1841 it was voted to build a fourth meeting house, and a change in location to the corner of Hammond and Main Streets was proposed. The congregation became divided over the issue, with parishioners on the south side of the Ox Pasture Brook favoring the move and those to the north side opposed to it. A vote was held and decided by a single vote, with 24 members in favor of re-location and 23 against. This resulted in a number of dissatisfied parishioners splitting off from the Rowley church and attending service in the neighboring Byfield parish.
The First Congregational Church of Rowley received official incorporation in 1889, and continues to serve the community today as a member of the United Church of Christ.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the administrative history of the church and the religious life of its members. It contains the earliest church, parish, and financial records beginning in 1664, as well as a "double" volume containing both personal notes of the Rev. Jedidiah Jewett and a listing of marriages. Additionally, there are microfilmed records replicating most of the physical volumes, and also including more recent administrative records dating after the church's incorporation in 1889.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Technical Requirements
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
"History." The Congregational Church of Rowley. Accessed October 3, 2019. http://www.firstchurchrowley.org/about/who-we-are/history-2/
Wheatland, Henry. Standard History of Essex County, Massachusetts: Embracing a History of the County from Its 1. Settlement to the Present Time, with a History and Description of Its Towns and Cities. (By Cyrus M Tracy Henry Wheatland). Boston: Jewett, 1878.
Davis, Emerson. Biographical Sketches of the Congregational Pastors of New England: Volume IV, n.d.
Baptismal records.; Church discipline.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Covenants (Church polity).; Installation (clergy).; Lord's Supper.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Ordination.; First Church (Rowley, Mass.); Rowley (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church records, 1664 1784; 1664-1784 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Digital Copies
  These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
  Scope and Contents
  This bound volume, also known as "The Phillips Diary", contains early records of both the church and the community in Rowley, including meeting minutes, church covenants, baptisms, marriages, and death lists recorded by Rev. Samuel Phillips. Further records include disciplinary matters, ecclesiastical councils, and other details of seventeenth-century life in the area.
- Microfilm records, 1664 1784; 1664-1784; 2010 (Reel Service Copy)
  This microfilm contains photographic copies of the Church records, 1664-1784, also known as the "Phillips Diary". This document is housed, as part of this collection, at the CLA.
- Microfilm records, 1664 1941; 1664-1941; 2007 (Reel 1, Reel 2, Reel 3)
  Restrictions on Access
  Only the service copy is available for library use. The archival master and print master copies are restricted for preservation purposes.
  This microfilm contains photographic copies of church records, parish records, treasurer's books, vital records, and ministerial records, some of the physical versions of which are part of this collection. A detailed listing of these follows:
  Reel 1
  CR I
  Church Records (also known as the "Phillips Diary"), 1664-1784
  CR II
  Church Records, 1742-1782
  CR III
  Church Records, 1782-1835
  Reel 2
  CR IV
  Vital Statistics and list of ministers, 1840-1870
  CR V
  Meetings, 1870-1920
  C Misc.
  Jedidiah Jewett's Extract Book, 1730-1783
  Church records pre-incorporation and Church Corporation Records, 1889-1941
  Reel 3
  PR I
  Parish Records, 1733-1782
  PR II
  Parish Records, 1781-1882
  PR III
  Parish Records, 1822-1870
  PT I
  Parish Treasurer, 1743-1832
  PT II
  Parish Treasurer, 1833-1862
  PR IV
  Parish Records, 1892-1903
- Church and parish records, 1728 1782; 1728-1782 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  This volume largely consists of church meeting minutes concerning the selection of new ministers – Jedidiah Jewett in 1728 and Jonathan Allin in 1780 – and records regarding their salaries.
- Jedidiah Jewett extract and marriage book, 1730 1783; 1730-1783 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  This bound book contains two volumes, each starting at opposite covers and using the righthand pages in its respective orientation. The "extract" portion contains Rev. Jedidiah Jewett's transcribed excerpts from philosophical and historical texts and local newspapers. The "marriage book" records marriages performed in the church.
- Microfilm records, 1730 1835; 1730-1835; 2008 (Reel Service Copy, Reel Archival Master, Reel Print Master)
  This microfilm contains photographic copies of Rev. Jedidiah Jewett's personal notebook, parish records, church records, and a treasurer's book, all of the physical versions of which are a part of this collection. A detailed listing of these follows:
  Section 1: C Misc.
  Jewett's Extract Book, 1730-1783
  Section 2: PR I
  Section 3: PR II
  Section 4: CR-PR
  Church Records and Parish Records, 1742-1782 and 1728-1763
  Section 5: CR III
  Section 6: PT I
- Parish records, 1733 1782; 1733-1782 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  This volume contains financial and administrative records, including church meeting minutes and financial information pertaining to officers' salaries and other expenditures.
- Financial records, 1743 1832; 1743-1832 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  This bound volume of records was kept by the church treasurers, and includes salary records for ministers and other church officers, pew rents, taxes, and other incomes and expenses relating to the running of the church.
- Parish records, 1781 1822; 1781-1822 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  This volume contains financial and administrative records, including church meeting minutes and financial information pertaining to officers' salaries and other expenditures. It also includes the results of an ecclesiastical council convened to resolve a dispute within the church.
- Church records, 1782 1835; 1782-1835 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  These records are primarily vital statistics and membership records, including admissions, dismissions, baptisms, marriages, and deaths. They also contain a number of disciplinary cases, mostly for intemperance or poor attendance on the Sabbath.